It wasn't until I was working with them
that I learned that they do not have
arrest powers.
>> And I said, I always thought MI6 was the
British CIA. MI5 was the British FBI.
They said, no, Scotland Yard is the
British FBI. I said, so what's MI5? He
said, we are domestic intelligence. We
spy on Britain's.
And I said, "I don't think I like that
at all."
>> By like by their doctrine and charter
that Wow.
>> Yeah.
>> I was not aware of that either.
>> I never heard that before.
>> Yeah. I thought they were externally
facing an anal an analogous to the
agency as well.
>> Yeah. They are, but they're only
domestic and they can't make arrests. I
said, "This this just turns my worldview
on its head." And they're like, "Yeah,
we're even worse than you guys are."
Yeah.
So, I think I fear that that's where
we're headed, even if it's in slow
motion. Again, it's been 25 years since
9/11.
>> So, but but I'm I'm worried that we've
got any number of intelligence a there
are 18 intelligence agencies in the US
government, which just flabbergasts
people overseas when you tell them that
because most countries have one. Some
big countries have two, like the Brits.
the Australians, the Canadians. We have
18. Like, do we really need 18 separate
intelligence services? Seriously,
>> come on.
>> I mean, I'm sure their budgets are
small. [laughter]
>> You know, I'd be comfortable paying more
taxes if they could show me where my tax
money went.
>> I I I would literally all
>> I would like that very much.
>> Let's just be transparent. Show me where
this money is going and
>> and I won't object. just just tell me
where it's going and I'd say, "Okay,
thank you. Go ahead. Spend spend my tax
money the way you see fit." Yeah.
>> Thanks for being transparent.
>> Yeah.
>> I'm not a betting man, John, but if I
was, we're not getting that.
>> I think [laughter]
I think we're not Oh, so I was going to
make a point, too.
I'm not saying that
people on Capitol Hill just have their
heads up their asses and they're not
interested in in oversight. A great part
of the problem is
using just the CIA as an example. I I I
don't know how many people are in the
CIA. It's classified anyway, 20, 30,
40,000 people. I don't have any idea.
But you can't oversee an agency that has
20, 30, 40,000 people with a staff of 40
on Capitol Hill. You can't do it. It's
not possible. And then you've got DNI on
top of it. besides
DIA, FBI, NSA,
Homeland Security, the uniform services,
intelligence services, you can't do it.
It's just not possible. I [snorts] think
we have to add to that too, the cottage
industry of people who leave
>> threeletter agencies and start
consultancy firms in the DC area or
>> everybody got rich. Everybody
>> and it's, you know, it's like, okay,
cool. These people don't work for the
agency. Not meaning necessarily the
we'll just call them the alphabet soup
organizations. Sure, they're not working
directly for that, but you're
contracting them to essentially do a job
that would be what they used to do and
now they can operate outside of certain
boundaries because of a tax status.
>> That's right.
>> That how do you even quantify or
calculate that as well too because that
although not directly associated with
those alphabet soup agencies are still
being paid through the budget of the you
know what I mean?
>> Yes.
>> It's a cottage industry and I know very
little about it but I know that it
exists. It's a not a revolving door
process, but like, hey, we got a problem
we need to solve. We can't do it
doctrally here. Who's getting close to
retirement? Hey man, here's your here's
your greased money train. I cannot even
begin to tell you how many people that I
worked with in the CIA's
counterterrorism center that would leave
work on Friday with a blue staff badge,
come back on Monday with a green
contractor badge, making three times
what they were making on Friday, sitting
in the same desk doing the same job. You
know, I say all the time too on
podcasts, it's not an accident that
before 9 911, the highest concentration
of millionaires in America was in
Silicon Valley and after 9/11, it was
Washington DC.
>> Is it really?
>> Mhm.
>> Damn. I mean, there certainly is a
business around war.
>> You got that right.
>> And it's ugly.
>> Yeah. And it goes forever because too
many people are getting rich. Why stop
it?
Man, [snorts] what are your thoughts on
the invasion of Iraq 2004?
Man, I argue with my dad on this one. I
was a young man in a profession of arms,
and I wanted what all young men want in
a profession of arms, somebody to fight.
My dad is a Vietnam veteran, and he was
like,
>> "Ah,
>> listen kid,
there's something wrong with the smell
of this cheese."
>> He was right. He was right. I still
haven't admitted that to him because he
can be right about nothing. So he will.
[laughter]
Now it's interesting now looking back at
it.
That plan to go into that country
predated 911 for sure.
>> Absolutely. Yes.
>> There's a famous story ring binder on
the shelf somewhere.
>> You know, I I
I I blew up on TikTok about
eight weeks ago. I would say
congratulations, but I'm not sure that's
a good thing.
>> Yeah, I I'm the juryy's still up.
[laughter] But one of the things that
really blew up that's taken on a life of
its own is this uh story
is this story that I tell about Colin
Powell calling me one morning, 1993. You
know, every every group in the CIA has a
morning meeting at 9:00. Every single
group. And you talk about what happened
overnight in the area that you cover.
And these meetings last 30 minutes and
then you start your day. [snorts]
And I go into the morning meeting and
the secretary walks in and she says,
"John," like with this puzzlement, she
says, "John, General Powell's on the
phone for you." And I said, "For me?" I
said, "How does General Pal know who I
am?" And she said, "I don't know, but he
asked for you by name." And I look at my
boss and he goes, "Well, go answer the
phone." So I go to my secure phone and I
said, "Good morning, General Pal. May I
help you?" He was the uh chairman of the
joint chiefs. I think at the time
he was chairman of the joint chiefs.
Clinton had just become president.
I said, "Good morning, General Pal. May
I help you?" And without missing a beat,
he says, "John, if the Iraqis were going
to kill the president, who would
actually be in charge of carrying out an
operation like that?"
>> It's a very pointed question.
>> Yeah. Very specific.
>> Yeah. And I said, if you're talking
about the attempt to assassinate former
President Bush,
all Kuwait operations are run from Iraq
uh Iraq's Basra station and Basra
station operations are run by the Iraqi
intelligence service director. Is that
is that Ibrahim Sabra Abdulaziz Adori?
And he says, "Where does he physically
sit?" And I said, "In Iraqi intelligence
service headquarters in Baghdad." And he
says, "Thank you." and he hangs up. So,
I go back in and everybody's waiting for
me. My boss said, "What do you want?" I
said, "He had a very specific question."
And I I told them. And we're like,
"Okay." And then we went on with the
meeting. 8 hours later, we fired 47
cruise missiles into Iraqi intelligence
service headquarters. And the reason why
this has taken on a life of its own is
because
the only person we killed was a janitor.
It was middle of the night, Iraq time,
and we killed the janitor. He was the
only person in the building. And I went
to the office the next day, and I said
to my boss, "I killed that janitor last
night."
>> And he said, "I knew you were going to
say that you didn't kill the janitor.
Powell killed the janitor. You didn't
know why Powell wanted the information.
And you did what you're trained to do.
You answered the man's question." But
it's always bothered me, you know, if if
we had killed Saddam Hussein, I would
have said,
>> "Yeah,
>> I killed Saddam Hussein. Y
>> where's my presidential medal of
freedom?" But it wasn't Saddam Hussein.
It was some poor guy probably had a
couple of kids at home. Never meant any
harm to anybody.
>> Why' they strike it at night?
>> You know, it was this weird [__] up
policy of the Clinton administration
that by God, we're going to show them
how tough we are. We don't want to kill
anybody cuz we don't want to be
bloodthirsty. So, we're going to do it
in the middle of the night. Okay. Well,
that they laugh at us when we do stupid
stuff like that.
>> Yeah.
>> So, anyway, there was this there was
this belief
all through the eight years of the
Clinton administration that we're going
to get these damn Iraqis. One of these
days, we're going to get them. It might
take us a while, but we're going to get
these bastards. And then there's a
famous story about
the 12th of September 2001, Richard
Pearl being at the White House telling
everybody who would listen. And he was
friends with all of them from Scoop
Jackson's office when they were young
men. Telling everybody, you know, we
have to attack Iraq, right? You know, we
have to attack Iraq, right?
So, the fix was in from the beginning.
What do they say? Never let a tragedy go
to waste. There it is.
That's that's the modern history of the
United States right there.
>> I'll be really curious to see how the
history books judge our involvement in
Iraq. Afghanistan I think was at least
more altruistic and why we execution
>> arguable for sure. Sure. But but the
reason to go into Afghanistan that was a
righteous war.
>> It was righteous. The beginning of it
was you know we had to destroy al-Qaeda.
We had to. They were saying Osama bin
Laden said that he was planning another
attack that would dwarf 911. So, we had
to stop them. They had murdered 3,000
Americans in one day.
>> That was a righteous war. Iraq was not
>> such a commitment of like America's
treasure. And I'm not talking about
money. Just the cascading consequences
of two decades. See, and that's another
thing, Andy, is there's never any, even
after war after war after war, there's
never any thought to the blowback. Like,
why do we never have that conversation?
It's easy to invade a country. I I said
this recently in an interview. It's easy
to invade a country. It's easy to
overthrow a government. The rest of it
is really, really hard. How do you get
out? And how do you get out without
leaving the place in a state of anarchy?
Look at Libya. We overthrew that
government in 2009
and it's still a in a state of chaos.
>> Yeah. I don't know why people think that
Iran will be any different.
>> Iran is the size of Western Europe. It
has 92 million people and a forbidding
topog topography.
>> Mhm.
>> How do we win something like that?
Unless you want to commit, you know,
400,000 troops, which we're not going to
do.
>> We tried that on their eastern and
western border.
>> Exactly.
>> Yes.
>> I look back at that now I'm like, okay,
not that I am arguing for eating the
delicious center of the Iraq Afghanistan
Oreo, [laughter]
but that's probably the time we have had
more military firepower and projection
of power on their eastern and western
border.
Yes, they death to America is a real
thing. Yes, largest state sponsor of
terrorism. Yes, we've had issues for
five decades.
>> Maybe it would have been a better idea
to handle it while we were already
there.
>> But I'm God,
>> you know, I remember when we first
attacked Iraq in early ' 03, we had to
go to the Iranians and say, "Listen,
we're going to cross your border a
couple of times. If we do, it's going to
be an accident. We don't intend to
remain. It might be one plane. It might
be one jeep full of guys. We mean
nothing by it. Our fight is with the
Iraqis. And the Iranians said, "Just
keep us out of it." And we were okay
with that. Just let us enrich our
uranium.
I
Nobody wants a nuclear Iran. I think we
can all agree on that.
>> Nobody does. I thought we destroyed
their nuclear capability last year and
now
>> I think the word was obliterated.
>> Yeah. And I don't know a lot about big
[clears throat] words, but I think I
know what that one is hinting at. And
then it's no like no, we had to go now
because it was at the tipping point. And
there's so much I mean I can't separate
the amount of external control Israel
may have over the decision-making of the
US. I don't I don't know what to make
sense of this [__] stew that people are
just pouring into with absolute
certainty about what it is that they're
saying which anybody who's absolutely
that sure about anything already scares
me. I love things like I believe I think
[laughter]
>> which is not what the terms that the
news use. I I don't know what to make
sense of it. I could see other countries
having influence and one thing I've
heard people say is well Israel came to
the US and they said either you do it or
we're going to use nukes,
>> right? So was this le I'm like well
there's other nuclear powers. So what if
Russia says hey you need to smash
Ukraine for us or we're going to use
nukes. Are we going to go do that next?
>> Right. Good question.
>> Well India says you know what we're
tired of these [__] on our border.
You either do something about Pakistan
or or we're going to like what does that
make us the world's [__] Like we just
go around and play nuclear cleanup. I
don't buy that.
>> See that? That's an oped right there.
>> That's an oped.
>> I don't know that.
>> That's a great that's a great line of
analysis. I I might steal it if you're
not if you're not going to publish it.
>> No, I'm not publishing [__] [laughter]
>> Nobody wants me to publish an op-ed.
First, I'd have to look up what the [__]
op-ed means, but and how you do that.
But that to me, again, it's the same
thing as Epstein. The AAMS razor
approach to me is the is the one that
makes the most sense to me. I also don't
come from the intelligence world. So,
I'm just trying to look at this
realistically.
It doesn't make there's too many other
people that could then and if they saw
if that was proven to be true, they'd be
lining up at like a lemonade stand to
pull that [__] To me, the saddest part
of this whole thing is that the JCPOA,
the joint comprehensive plan of action,
it was working. You know, whether or not
twothirds of the Senate uh ratified it,
the answer is no, they didn't. whether
or not it became partisan, it was
working. It was almost exactly the same
deal that we had through the United
Nations with Saddam Hussein's government
through um
uh the UN Security Council Resolution
986, right? Unannounced
uh inspections by United Nations weapons
inspectors, lead seals, cameras going in
every direction 24/7. It was actually
working. I get that Donald Trump didn't
want Barack Obama to have that kind of a
foreign policy win. I get it. But
withdrawing us unilaterally from the
JCPOA put us back at square one again.
>> And what we're hoping to get now
um
is the exact same language that was in
the JCPOA.
no uranium enrichment and we want to
inspect the nuclear sites and we want
them to be sealed. Okay, we already had
all that and we withdrew. So now you
want to renegotiate the the same
agreement and how many what with 13
people have died on our side already for
what? For nothing. For literally
nothing.
>> This is why now you're going to get me
started now here. We need to operate
utterly independently of the Israelis.
I've said a million times. I'm going to
repeat it. Starting in the mid1 1980s
when Ronald Reagan was president, every
single Israeli prime minister, no matter
who it was, when they came to the United
States, and they come all the time, they
would say, "Please attack Iran. Please
attack Iran. Please attack Iran." And
every single president said, "I'm not
going to do it."
Obama said what, two weeks ago that
Netanyahu came and said, "If you don't
attack Iran, we're going to use nuclear
weapons." And Obama said, "Go ahead. Go
ahead, use them." And he called the
bluff. And they didn't use them. Since
1986,
the Iranians have been 6 months away
from a nuclear weapon. Well, guess what?
No, they're not. That's a lie. There
have been two, count them, two national
intelligence estimates. What a national
intelligence estimate is is it's a sense
of the community of the intelligence
community formal paper
and this is important. If the CIA writes
a paper okay congratulations this is the
CIA believes this or DIA believes that
or state department believes this other
thing. An NIE, National Intelligence
Estimate, is you have all 18
intelligence agencies sitting around a
giant table in the offices of the
National Intelligence Council and
they're going sentence by sentence.
Okay, the first sentence is and the the
National Intelligence Officer reads it.
Anybody have any objections? And all 18
people get to weigh in. It takes weeks
normally to coordinate a paper like
this. All 18 intelligence agencies
concluded decisively twice that the
Iranians did not have a nuclear weapons
program.
>> How recent were these?
>> The first one was 2003
and the other one was like 2009
something like that. And in addition,
Ayatah Kamayi issued a fatwa saying that
it was a sin to develop a nuclear weapon
and that's why they were not enriching
to weaponsra
levels.
>> Yeah.
>> And the Israelis said they didn't give a
[__] They want us to bomb bomb bomb.
>> So finally we did.
>> The meeting that you're talking about
where there first off I'm surprised that
any you fill a room with 18 different
agencies. I'm actually surprised
anything ever in the world gets
accomplished. I'm not exaggerating when
I tell you I never hated anything in my
entire career as much as coordinating an
NIE. I was the deputy national
intelligence officer for a while. Um,
and then to get promoted to GS14,
I had to write an NIE. So I wrote this
NIE in 19
and it was called Iraq colon Saddam's
next 12 months
and we coordinated it in 8 hours and the
national intelligence officer Ben Bon
God rest his soul terrific guy he came
to me afterwards and he said that was
the fastest coordination session for an
NIE that I've seen in 25 years and I
said this one was Actually pretty easy,
Ben. Saddam could threaten Kuwait.
Saddam could threaten the Kurds. Saddam
could threaten the Shia. Saddam will
probably try to violate sanctions.
>> Yeah,
>> big deal.
>> So, [clears throat] are those NIEs in
layman's terms, are they a way to assess
risk and then you can brief the policy
makers?
>> That's exactly what they're for. And so
the reason I asked this is it's
listening to Tulsi Gabbard testify
>> and she said essentially I'm
paraphrasing Michael if you could pull
it up that Trump is the
single or sole individual that
determines the immediacy of the threat.
>> Mhm.
>> I feel like that premise is incredibly
dangerous.
>> It is dangerous. But and I also don't
know is that is that a real assessment
because wouldn't an organization or
organizations create something like an
NIE and he would be able to I'm assuming
that that is the role of intelligence
organizations and and and maybe this is
a gross misunderstanding of what she was
saying but if that's the case what if
one day after we're done with Iran he
goes Mexico is an imminent threat like
is it really like that? Like the guy
sitting in the chair with the Diet Coke
button gets to just determine it like
that.
>> This the answer.
>> Am I a misunderstanding?
>> No, no, you you've hit it on the head.
The answer to the question is very
complicated. So the CIA really any
intelligence service I should say
>> sole individual authorized to determine
what constitutes an imminent threat. I
thought that that was the role of the
intelligence apparatus. The intelligence
apparatus will say the intelligence
community does not believe that Iran is
an imminent threat. The president can
elect to ignore that. So technically,
sure, he's the decision maker. He's the
one that's going to make the final call.
Any other president in modern American
history has been surrounded by, you
know, the best and the brightest, and
this guy was a professor at Harvard, and
this guy was the deputy assistant
secretary of whatever, and this guy, you
know, whatever. you you surround
yourself with people who know these
things, the Henry Kissingers of their
day, although I hate to use that
example, but you know what I mean.
>> Um, so technically the president is the
final authority on these issues, but any
other president will ask the secretary
of state, what do you think? Secretary
of Defense, what do you think? National
Security Adviser, what do you think? CI
director, what do you think? And
everybody's going to weigh in. And then
these are his top people. He's gonna in
concert with them come to a policy
decision.
>> Collaborative effort.
>> A collaborative effort. And remember
that the CIA is not a policy
organization. It is a policy support
organization.
George W. Bush did something that was
very very controversial. Just as I was
leaving the agency in the president's
daily brief, which is, you know, six
days a week, 16 pages, the the first
article is a full page. After that,
there are a couple of articles of a
paragraph of fact and a paragraph of
analysis.
Um, he ordered the CIA to put a
paragraph of fact, a paragraph of
analysis, and a paragraph entitled
policy recommendation.
>> Well, that flies in the face of
everything that the CIA is. You're
supposed to be the one that makes the
policy, not the CIA. The CIA can tell
you what the facts are and what the
facts likely mean, but then you make a
decision. That only lasted for George W.
Bush's second term and then it went back
to its normal state of equilibrium.
My point being,
sure, Donald Trump is the last person.
But then Trump told 60 Minutes, not most
in the mo most recent um interview, the
one before when asked, "Who are your
[clears throat] closest adviserss?" He
said, "I don't have any. I just go with
my gut." And we've not had a president
like that before.
>> That is a bold mission statement.
>> Yeah, it is. It's very, very bold. Very
gutsy.
>> Yeah. Another thing like to see what
>> do you mind searching to see when those
NIEs were NIE on Iran the Iran nuclear
program?
>> I tell you what I would like to have
looked at very deeply perhaps rewritten
is the authorized use of military force.
[snorts]
>> That's a tall order.
>> See, but here again you've got
manipulated and bent president since its
inception.
>> Yes. And you've got these cowards on
Capitol Hill. We got 20
>> 2007 and 2003. I thought it was three
and nine. Three and seven.
>> Yeah, the AUMF provides
some immense latitude.
>> It's uh
sometimes I'll get online and people
think I'm arguing or uh what was the
term somebody used? They called me
pedantic. So, I had to look that I had
to look that one up because they're
like, "We're at war." I'm like, "No,
we're not."
>> No, we're not.
>> And we're not. And the point is, isn't
that [__] ridiculous?
>> Yes.
>> That we can do this. They what they
think, again, I had to look up the word
pedantic, and now I try to use it every
day because it's really good. But
[laughter]
>> somebody called me mercurial the other
day.
>> That's a good one, too.
>> I had to look it up.
>> Yeah. But it's it baffles me that we can
do every action that looks exactly like
warfare.
>> Yeah.
>> But not as a country declared as war.
And again, it's it's a way where actions
can be taken without the oversight that
I want to see.
>> Unacceptable.
>> But and then people are like, "Oh, it's
a political issue." But guess what? Your
team captain
>> did the ex He bent the [__] out of this,
too.
>> That's right.
>> Blue and red. They've manipulated the
[__] out of this.
>> We have not declared war on on anybody
since
>> Vietnam.
>> No, we never declared war.
>> No, I'm sorry. Since before Vietnam.
>> Yeah. Yeah. It was World War II. Yeah.
On December 8th, we declared war on
Japan. And the next day, we declared war
on Germany. And that's it. That was the
last time. Even Korea wasn't a war. It
was a police action. What do you think
it would take to change that thing? I
don't think Well, first off, I don't
think people realize the powers that it
provides and the off-ramp,
>> at least in the short term, to oversight
that are foundational documents were
written upon.
>> Why would we want that?
>> I know, right? The Constitution is so
crystal clear on these issues. It It
makes the executive, the legislative,
and the judicial branches of government
co-equal
branches. Co-equal. And then you have
these clowns like Lindsey Graham saying,
"I want to make Congress weaker."
It's like, "Are you out of your mind?"
An argument could be made.
>> Yes. [laughter] There's a lot of stuff
that we could say about Lindsey Graham.
>> For clarity, an argument could be made
about me as well on that. It's, you
know, you [laughter] know, there's
strong arguments and weaker arguments,
but it's
>> I don't Yeah.
>> I And people national security
>> safety. What's the saying? Somebody
willing to sacrifice liberty for
security is is Yeah.
>> Deserves either. Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> I have never seen the government give
the power back.
>> No. Ever. Ever. it we have to come to
some catastrophe
like that which resulted in the in the
uh church committee before there's any
real change like structural change.
>> Yeah. And then is the system so far
outgrown or so far outside of the lines
that they're supposed to color in?
>> Could it even be put back in or
reoriented back in? I don't know the
answer to that. You know, it's different
now, too, than it was in 1975 just
because of the state of technology.
Like, how do you put that genie back in
the bottle?
>> I love the shorts of you on the diary of
the CEO just blowing people's minds with
what the agency can do.
>> I mean, Vault 7,
>> all of that's public. How is it that
nobody paid any attention to that? It's
all public.
>> I only think that they're doing it to
our enemies.
>> Yeah. And then the reality is that's not
true.
>> No, they can do it to all of us.
>> How do Okay, how does somebody survive
in an electronic world? Like what how
does you know we got to all turn into
Ted Kazinski is [laughter] what is what
it comes down to. You live in a shack in
Idaho.
>> Yeah. No, I think it was Montana.
>> Montana.
>> Yeah. Somebody bought his shack. They
have it I think as their like lawnmower
storage.
>> Oh my god. Can you imagine?
>> Yeah. I can't get behind the bombing
campaign, but under like going on like a
little tech break, I totally understand.
>> Yeah, I get it.
>> But even then, in a world where
everybody is defined by their
technological usage, just like my wife
doing accidental SDRs, you might end up
on their radar because like this guy has
got some amazing fieldcraft. He's a
ghost. Like no, he just hates
>> Yeah, [laughter] he's a lite. That's
all. He's a lite. Ah, but I mean,
>> how do how do you operate in a world
where they can reach into basically
anything that is powered?
>> Mhm. And take it over.
>> Do you just I mean, is it just forced
acceptance? I mean, it's not like you
and I can stop it. You can tell as many
people that it has happening as
possible.
>> I'm sitting on my cell phone right now,
and I know you are, too.
>> Oh, yeah. NSA is with us, right? Hello,
NSA. I You guys should get a budget
increase. Good job.
>> Yeah. I there are a couple of little
things that I've done like uh you know
Tucker Carlson's got this uh or he
advertises this uh cell phone like
encrypted cell phone.
>> Yeah, but I could point you back to the
agency making a cell phone for the
specific usage of invading drug cartels.
>> Well, I don't [laughter] I don't have
one of his cell phones. You're exactly
right. I don't want to have a cell
phones, but it got me to thinking. And
so, um, I went I I went to an electronic
store in Europe and I just bought a cell
phone and I was able to register it in
in another name. And I have a spare SIM
card. I can pop out my SIM card, pop
this one, and this is registered in a
Middle Eastern country. So, wherever I
happen to be, I'll just go into the
local version of Radio Shack or or Best
Buy or whatever.
>> Yep.
>> And I'll buy a I'll buy a burner phone
or I'll buy a SIM card and swap them
out.
>> But even that's not going to
>> Yeah.
>> really protect me in the long run.
>> Yeah. That'll give you that give you a
little bit of a head start. They're
going to find you a
>> little bit. Oh, they'll find you.
>> Especially with the computing power.
>> That That's another one. Like
>> I mean 25 years ago, that's how we got
out as a beta.
>> Yeah. He he made one single mistake. He
he accessed his emails with a landline.
>> John, that was it. I was killing people
because of their SIM cards. See,
>> 2005.
>> I mean,
>> they learned though. They learned quick.
>> Yeah, they did.
>> And we adapted. But yeah, it's, you
know, these NSA databases and and just
data farms that are showing up and odd
locations and it's like, oh, every
single like, we're not looking through
it, though. We're just storing it,
>> right?
>> Yeah. You're not looking just in case
now. [laughter]
>> Yeah. Then why do you need this gigantic
facility in Utah that you've built?
Because we might need to look at it
later.
>> Yeah.
>> And then depending on who's throwing
>> without a warrant, by the way,
>> that's the biggest thing that bugs me
that I either the Constitution matters
or it doesn't. Either it means something
to be an American. And I truly still
believe that we can be a beacon to the
world, but we don't do that by hiding
our missteps. We have to be honest about
where we have fallen short and we have
to learn from our mistakes.
>> And that last one right there, I'm not
so sure that we're actually doing.
>> I have to agree.
>> I have to agree. It's like we reinvent
the wheel every time we elect a new
president.
>> Yeah. And that's where I landed. I don't
think this is a top down fix. I think
it's a bottom up fix generational.
>> Mhm.
>> And I I have uh three children. I have a
my daughter I'm getting ready to get
into birthday season. So I'll have 18,
21, and 23.
>> Wonderful.
>> They're fantastic. I'm loving their
skepticism and good.
>> Yeah, it's it's healthy. I don't I don't
like throw fire on it and like fashion
them like tinfoil berets or anything
like that, but [snorts]
>> I I like it. Michael's an example, too.
I mean, he's 23 years old. He's, you
know, his views of the world and the way
he thinks about things and his response
to what he is seeing being put out
nationally and globally. I ask him about
it all the time
>> because he also has a different optic
than you and I have had based off of our
previous careers. And
>> the answers are very informative. The
pendulum, I don't know if we have like
bounced off of where it's swinging to,
but it is going to come back.
>> It has to.
>> And I think the country will survive.
I'm not saying a tire or two might not
go off the track, but I think we're
going to be okay, right?
>> Because of what I see from the younger
generation.
>> Good.
>> I'm hopeful.
>> I am, too.
>> Maybe I'm being too incredibly
optimistic, dude. On that note, I mean,
there's such a difference between the
price and the cost.
>> I mean, when you signed up to serve at
the agency,
>> you pay that price. And it's the same
thing as military service. You know how
long you're going to enlist for, and you
know that there's risk associated with
that.
>> The cost though is everything you can
never calculate. the strain on family,
the the time away,
>> how has everything that has happened to
you, like
>> and I'm sure it's changed over time, but
like with your children,
>> how did it impact them or your
relationship with them? It
>> it was devastating.
>> Yeah.
>> I have five children. I have four boys
and a girl. Boy, boy, boy, girl, boy.
Um, four of them don't speak to me
>> still to this day.
>> One I'm very close to. We speak almost
every day. um
>> and then start at the time where you uh
I mean
>> yeah I was still in
>> well and the reason I I mean you have
talked on so many large platforms about
a lot of the things that you did in the
agency so I'd rather just talk to you as
a person you know what I mean and so
people can go and re go watch Diary of
the CEO and just watch when he's talking
to him about how they can turn the
speaker on a TV into a microphone I'm
like oh yeah they definitely can do that
and he's just like what I'm like yeah
dude they got you [laughter]
everybody knew that you [snorts] and I
knew that a lot of people don't want to
believe they have those abilities. So,
people can go reference that. But, you
know, to me, I I had a time period when
I was going through my divorce where I
lost 18 months with my oldest son. Very
close now. I think our relationship is
better.
>> Oh, thank God.
>> Well, and I hope that that can be the
case for you with your other kids.
>> I'm optimistic.
>> Did the relationship break when things
started becoming public about what had
happened with you at the agency?
>> Yes.
>> God damn.
>> Yes. Yeah. I'll get there. I I'm
optimistic.
>> Yeah. People often accuse me of being
irrationally optimistic, overly
optimistic, but I prefer to live my life
like that. And and I I'm I'm hopeful and
relatively confident that things are
going to work out.
>> How old are they?
>> Uh 33, 30,
>> 21, 19, and 14.
>> I think sometimes
they have to get their own laps around
the sun.
>> Mhm.
>> It's uh agreed.
I there are I understand
yet don't agree with the criticism of
what you did by coming forward. I
understand the people that say that in
my opinion I wish there were more people
who were like you who were serving in
the agency. Thank you very much
>> because I saw it firsthand, you know,
and we were often times the action arm
of the intelligence
>> in air.
>> Very much so.
>> And
>> you were
>> and it's not perfect and everybody is
doing the best that they can, but to me
it's it's a rare thing to be issued the
flag of your country and not rent it,
you know, or go buy it on a t-shirt,
which everybody can do what they want
to, but it has to mean something to me.
>> And uh and from people the outside, they
can criticize what you did because they
don't have an understanding of it. And
more importantly, they don't have a skin
in the game.
>> No, they don't.
>> And you know, I say I'm not I'm not
trying to [__] on people, but any slob
can roll out of bed and write a nasty
comment on a YouTube page.
>> Yeah.
>> So, I I try hard just to ignore all that
noise. Remember this. Joe has said this
many times. He's never encountered
somebody in life who is living an
enriching,
successful, joyfilled life that spends
their time being an [__] on the
internet.
>> Ah, that's that's great. I mean, it it
really helps you reenter
>> and often times now I will respond to
people
>> and just say, "Listen, I don't know
what's going on in your life,
>> but I truly hope that whatever it is
that you're dealing with gets better."
Because people who are doing well, they
don't act like this. Most of the time,
you'll get a middle finger emoticon.
But I hope that it I hope that it sticks
with them. And it goes to the point
>> Yeah.
>> about the kids
more laps and more context.
If you can keep showing them who you
are, I think you're going to be
>> I think you're right. And and I'm very
hopeful in that respect. And I've I've
also
made very clear to every one of them
that I'm a phone call away.
>> Mhm.
>> That's all they have to do.
>> I did the same thing with my son, too.
>> And one day the phone rang
>> and it changed everything.
>> That That's what I'm hoping for.
>> That 18 months felt like about 18
decades.
>> Yes.
>> For clarity.
>> Um and it was it was all tied around the
time period of that divorce, but and I
get it. He was the oldest, probably the
most impacted by it. had a had a
processing ability that probably let him
go down just a mental rabbit holes of
the wise and the just the five W's, you
know.
>> Mhm.
>> Um,
>> good. All you
>> I'm glad that happened for for both of
you.
>> All you can do and the only thing I
could do was consistently
be the best version, try to be the man
that I wanted to be, which I still fall
short every day.
>> But to show him that example,
>> they'll come back around, man.
>> They'll come back around. God willing,
I'm hopeful. Families are a bastard. You
know, I wonder too if if it's something
about this generation specifically. I've
I've tried to do as much reading about
family estrangement as I can. There are
a lot of really good books out there
right now.
>> It's a really common issue actually.
>> And that's exactly what I was going to
say. I I saw something on the news just
yesterday saying that 25% of all
American families are experiencing some
level or form of family estrangement.
And it's easy to think you're alone. I
have a I have a friend, she used to
write to me when I was in prison. She
was a Broadway star from the 60s and now
she's almost 90 years old and we call
each other every few weeks. her son. She
has one child. Her son, who's now well
into his 50s, just cut her off like 10
years ago, 12 years ago now, just cold
turkey cut her off.
>> She doesn't have any idea why. She
called me one day and she asked me if I
knew of a good private investigator. I
said, "Oh yeah, I know a very good
private investigator." And I connected
them and she hired him. I didn't ask her
why she wanted him. was her business.
But he told me all she wanted was a
picture of her granddaughter.
>> She had never met her granddaughter. And
so he kind of, you know, he parked
across the street from the school and um
and figured out who her granddaughter
was and took a picture.
But not a, you know, a minute goes by
that she's not thinking about
>> Yeah. the son that she doesn't
understand how she lost or why she lost
and the granddaughter that she's never
met. She doesn't have very much more
time left on on earth. Kind of the
harder realization is in that too is
that the situation may not change. It
may never change.
>> Yeah. I suspect if it hasn't by now her
husband died, the guy's father and um
and the guy never reacted or responded
in any way.
>> Yeah.